Welcome to Dealmakers. I'm Sarah Sharp.
I'm a real mergers and acquisitions deal
attorney who helps people buy and sell
businesses every day. I'm going to tell
you one of the biggest things that
disrupts the deal process. Sometimes it
makes it not go through at all.
Sometimes it delays it by months or even
years and it's almost never on the top
of mind for a buyer or a seller. And
that thing is the commercial lease. So,
if you're buying a business and you're
looking, it has a physical office space,
you need to change the way you're
looking at it and make sure that
addressing the lease issue is absolutely
top of mind the whole time. LOI going
forward. Before I explain what I'm
saying a little bit more, please like
and subscribe to this channel if you
find it valuable. Check out
dealacademy.org where you could become
the actual expert on a lot of these
pieces of the deal process. So, let's
say that you're buying a business and it
has an office space. There's a lot of
reasons the landlord can tank your deal
and for some reason it's just not top of
mind for people. They know that they
need to work out the bank for financing.
They know they need to do diligence and
interact with the seller so they can
take the business over. They need
lawyers to draft agreements kind of this
nebulous like contract concept. But for
some reason, landlord negotiations falls
way to the bottom of people's list and
they forget about it well until the end
of the whole deal process. And then for
the first time, they approach the
landlord and say, "Hey, can you sign
some documents for me? I'm taking over
the lease space." And they're completely
shocked when the landlord says, "Who the
bleep are you? I have no interest in
letting this other person off the lease,
and I'm not really interested in letting
you into the space I own either." that
can completely tank your deal. Lot of
reasons for that. Some of them are
obvious, right? If you're buying a
business and people are coming in person
and you're trying to retain those people
with that minimal disruption, changing
where those people have to go to is a
pretty disruptive event. So, a lot of
people are going to want to buy
businesses and keep them in the same
place. Another reason is if you're
getting a bank loan, sometimes the bank
is going to require that you keep the
same office space and that you assume
the lease. So, if you're the seller,
it's you assign the lease or you
subleasase. And if it's the buyer,
you're assuming the lease obligations.
That can be critical to your seller
because often these commercial leases
are incredibly oppressive and they're on
the shoulders of the person running the
business, it's a pretty big burden for
them from an overhead perspective. And
almost always they've personally
guaranteed it. So, if they are going to
take $4 million for the sale of their
business and it turns out they still
have $20,000 a month lease payment they
can't get out of, then you know for the
next 5 years, it's going to really tank
the economics for them. So, the lease is
enormous and that that's a very normal
thing that happens all the time in my
deals. That will be the dynamic. I mean,
these commercial leases are expensive.
They're impossible to get out of. You
have personally guaranteed them. So the
landlord doesn't care if you've sold
your business and commercial real estate
isn't hopping. So the landlord, even if
they're decently reasonable people,
might not be able to find anybody else
to come in very easily and pay that same
amount. So they're going to keep
charging it to the seller. If that's
going to happen, the seller might not
want to sell. It's important to know
that way at the beginning. So you're
probably I'm guessing there's at least a
couple people who are watching this
video and going, "No, no, no. My seller
said that he has a great relationship
with the landlord. And oh my gosh, I've
heard that 1 million times and it has
panned out like once. They all think
they have a great relationship with the
landlord, but they're not asking this of
the landlord. They don't know how the
landlord's going to respond to this. So,
imagine it for a second from your
landlord's position, right? I'm a
landlord. I have an office space. I have
a lovely tenant who's been there for
four years. Caused me no problems. I
love him. I have a great relationship
with this guy. He is fantastic. I hope
he stays there forever. All of a sudden,
he tells me, "Next week, I'm selling my
business and some guy you don't know or
woman you don't know is going to buy
it." And then, you know, they're going
to pay you rent probably. I don't know
exactly what their plans are and I have
no control over it, but can you sign
these documents? And the landlord
thinks, "Why? You're obligated under
this to continue paying me for the next
6 years. Why am I going to let you off
the hook for that so I get the same
amount that you were going to pay me
from some less reliable stranger who I
don't have any relationship with? Like,
what's the motivation from the
landlord's perspective there? You can
imagine how hard it can be from a
negotiation strategy perspective to
negotiate with somebody who doesn't have
any. You have nothing to offer basically
like please let me stay at your place.
I'm gonna pay you exactly what that guy
was paying you and you don't know me
from Adam is a hard position to take
when you're negotiating. It's necessary,
but you know, you've got to recognize
that you don't have a ton of negotiation
capital there. Additionally, with the 7A
loan, often the bank is going to require
a landlord waiver and release or it's
called a landlord waiver and subregation
agreement. Check it out on sba.gov. You
can see example versions of the way that
people have to present these documents
to the landlord to say, "Hey, in
addition to letting me, a stranger, take
over this lease, could you also sign
this really intimidating document from
the federal government that says that
you have very little to any rights as it
relates to the business if I stop paying
everybody?" I think it's most fair to
categorize this as asking someone a
favor. That is okay. Maybe the seller
does have a great relationship with the
landlord. that's wonderful. But saving
all of this negotiation and favorite
asking till the very end is usually a
bad idea and it can really derail your
closing experience. It can scuttle the
deal entirely for the reasons I
mentioned before and it's just not
something to put off. The sellers often
will say, "I don't want to tell my
landlord till I'm really sure that the
deal is going to go through." And that's
a really good time to work with them on
different ways that you can give that
seller some reassurance that you're
serious. You might want to sign your
purchase agreement with very few
contingencies. Sometimes people sign
purchase agreements that say this is
condition precedent. It's conditioned on
the landlord agreeing to me taking over
the space so that at least the seller
knows that you're guaranteeing you're
going to buy the business if you can, if
you can get financing as long as the
landlord lets you. There's different
ways to bring that comfort level in. But
saving your discussions and your
negotiations and your favor asking of
the landlord until the fourth quarter is
just so inadvisable and it will
absolutely bite you about 50 to 70% of
the time. If you found this valuable,
please like and subscribe or check out
dealacademy.org
and become the expert and avoid other
ways that your deal might be scuttled or
delayed.